好吧，让我们开始吧，欢迎回到这是第九次演讲
okay let's uh let's get going welcome
back this is a ninth lecture of the
浓缩当然是几个视频中的一些快速事项
condensed matter of course a couple of
quick things first of all the the videos
从他们开始在线上的讲座中可以找到他们
from the lectures they're starting to
appear online you can get to them
如果您想尝试一下，它们已从我的网页链接了，请再次观看
they're linked from my web page if you
want to try them out watch them again if
您发现它很有用，如果您对该技术有任何疑问，请告诉我
you find it's useful let me know if you
have any trouble with the technology
到目前为止，它仍在故障排除中，还有留言板
where it's still troubleshooting some
things also the message board so far
人们没有那么多地使用它，请不要害羞，我保证你会
people haven't used it all that much
please don't be shy I promise you'll
觉得它很有帮助，所以在这一点上，我们大约是课程的三分之一
find it helpful so at this point we're
about a third the way through the course
所以值得停下来一秒钟，盘点一下我们在哪里
so it's it's worth sort of stopping for
a second and taking stock of where we
到目前为止，我们去过的地方和去过的地方，我们一直在寻找
are and where we've been and where we're
going so far we've really been looking
试图建立某种微观的理解
at trying to build up some sort of
microscopic understanding of the
材料的宏观特性我们从几个比较粗糙的材料开始
macroscopic properties of materials we
started with a couple of rather crude
材料的图片，然后我们开始查看更详细的信息
pictures of materials and then we
started looking at more detailed
材料，但只在一个维度上，所以最终我们希望有一些
materials but only in one dimension so
eventually we'd like to have some
材料的详细图片，但是在三个维度上，我们将转向
detailed pictures of materials but in
three dimensions so we're going to turn
我们现在关注三个维度，这实际上使我们的生活
our attention to three dimensions now
and this actually makes our life a
有点困难，有点复杂，但这是
little bit more difficult a little bit
more complicated but but this is the
描述真实材料的最终目标，在这一点上值得
eventual objective to describe real
materials and at this point it's worth
回想我在第一次演讲中说的一件事
thinking back to one of the things that
I said in the very first lecture that
凝聚态物理世界极为广阔而多样，一旦我们
the world of condensed matter physics is
extremely broad and diverse and once we
了解原子之间如何相互键合，您知道离子共价
understand how it is that atoms bond to
each other you know an ionic covalent
氢金属或范德华力键可以开始建立巨大的
hydrogen metallic or Vander Waals bonds
you can start building up an enormous
各种不同的材料进行研究，因此似乎我们应该进行
variety of different materials to study
and so it seems appropriate that we do a
某些类型的凝结物质的强制性游览
little bit of an obligatory tour of some
of the types of condensed matter that
我们实际上并不会专注于此，但是值得一提
we're not actually going to focus on but
that are out there and are worth knowing
至少它们存在，所以这里只是一些浓缩的例子
that at least that they exist so here
are just a few examples of condensed
物质物理学这是我们要去的一种凝聚态物理学
matter physics this is the one type of
condensed matter physics we are going to
研究结晶固体，我还有很多要说的
study the crystalline solids and I'll
have a whole lot more to say about
后来关于结晶固体的一般概念，是否有些
crystalline solids later on the general
idea of a crystalline solid is it some
原子的周期性排列，通常是宏观的
sort of periodic arrangement of atoms
and very frequently the macroscopic
晶体的形态反映了您的基础结构
morphology of the of the crystal
reflects its underlying structure as you
可以在这张图片中看到这张水晶的特定图片是
can sort of see in this in this picture
this particular picture of crystal is is
石英二氧化硅在美丽的faul晶体中，您可以看到它
quartz silicon dioxide in a beauty
faul crystal and you can see that its
结构以某种方式反映了原子如何被组合在一起
structure somehow is reflecting how the
atoms are put together one can also have
晶体类型稍微复杂一些，而在大多数晶体中
slightly more complicated types of
crystals whereas in most crystals in
这些晶体原子可以通过离子或共价键结合在一起
these crystals atoms are held together
in ionic or covalent bonds you can have
Vander Waals键非常重要的情况，所以在此图中
situations where Vander Waals bonds are
extremely important so in this picture
这就是所谓的分子晶体，这里发生的是你有很多
this is known as a molecular crystal
what happens here is you have a lot of
原子聚在一起形成一个分子，它们牢固地结合在分子中
atoms coming together to form a molecule
they're strongly bonded in the molecule
通过共价键或离子键，然后分子聚在一起形成一个
via covalent or ionic bonds but then the
molecules come together to form a
晶体在这种情况下分子之间的键非常弱
crystal where the it's very weak bonding
between the molecules in this case
范德华勒斯（Vander Waals）粘合了这张特殊的照片，描绘了C 60 60碳
Vander Waals bonds this particular
picture is a depiction of C 60 60 carbon
原子聚在一起形成足球形状，或者如果您位于
atoms coming together to make a soccer
ball shape or if you're on this side of
海洋，这是一种足球形状，我想在足球的另一面是
the ocean it's a football shape I guess
on the other side of football is a
无论如何，它们的形状都不同，所以它们聚在一起形成这些C 60分子
different shape anyway so they come
together to make these C 60 molecules
和C 60分子是非常不活泼的物种，但它们仍然可以结合
and the C 60 molecules they're very
inactive species but they can still bond
可以通过范德华力结合在一起形成晶体
together forming to form a crystal via
Vander Waals bonding one can have
情况有些不那么井井有条的情况
situations where you have a something
where it's not so organized a little bit
更无序的是无定形固体
more disordered this is what's known as
an amorphous solid the word amorphous
来自希腊语，没有形式，显然该对象具有某种形式
comes from Greek meaning without form
obviously the object has form of some
排序，但它是无序形式，这是二氧化硅的另一种描述，但
sort but it's a disordered form this is
another depiction of silicon dioxide but
是无定形二氧化硅，这里的微观结构是蓝色
it's amorphis silicon dioxide the
microscopic structure here the blue
物体应该是硅，红色物体是氧气
objects are supposed to be silicon and
the and the red objects are oxygen every
硅与四个氧键合每个氧与两个硅键合
silicon is bonded to four oxygen every
oxygen is bonded to two silicon's and
通常我们熟悉这种无定形二氧化硅作为窗口
generally we are familiar with this
silicon dioxide amorphous as window
玻璃具有与其晶体表弟石英相同的许多特性，但它
glass has a lot of the same properties
as its crystalline cousin quartz but it
是一种略有不同的材料，我们也可以具有无序的结构，例如
is a slightly different material we can
also have disordered structures such as
这里的液体和液体之间原子之间的吸引力
liquids there here and in liquids
there's attraction between atoms or
分子，但是将其保持在永久配置中并不是那么牢固
molecules but it's not so strong to keep
it held in a permanent configuration the
原子仍然可以有足够的热能来回移动，这使得
the atoms can still have enough thermal
energy to move around and that gives the
流动它可以流动的属性，您可能会遇到一些情况
liquid its property that it can flow you
can have situations where you
具有一定流动性和一定结晶度的部分顺序
a partial order with a some amount of
flowing in some amount of crystallinity
或剩余的订单数量，因此这张图片被称为
or some amount of order that remains so
this picture is known as what's known as
液晶剩下的顺序是所有这些分子
a liquid crystal the order that remains
is that all of these molecules these
看起来像鱼雷或Orzo的东西都保持了方向
things that look like torpedoes or orzo
are they all retain their orientation
它们都朝着相同的方向倾斜，并且都排成一排，但是
they're all angled to the same direction
and they all line up in stacks but
在每个堆栈中它们都是无序的，它们实际上可以在堆栈中流动
within each stack they're disordered and
they can actually flow within the stack
这就是使它们成为液晶的原因，并且种类繁多
and that's what makes them a liquid
crystal and there's a huge variety of
液晶取决于您保留的订单类型和类型
liquid crystals depending on what type
of order you retain and what type of
秩序在混乱和混乱之间被抛弃了一半
order gets thrown away halfway between
the disorder and disorder is also the
准晶体的想法这个特殊的图片就是所谓的
idea of the quasi crystal this
particular picture is what's known as a
彭罗斯（Penrose）瓷砖以罗杰·彭罗斯（Roger Penrose）最著名的数学家之一的名字命名
Penrose tile named after Roger Penrose
one of the most famous mathematicians
在牛津，这里是世界上最著名的数学家之一
here at Oxford one of the most famous
mathematicians in the world actually
无论如何，这是由两种不同类型的瓷砖组成的，这些蓝色的小蓝
anyway this is made up of two different
types of tiles these little blue blue
对象和这些绿色的小对象，它们堆叠在一起适合
objects and these little green objects
and they stack together they fit
完美地结合在一起，这是一些非常有序的安排，但实际上
perfectly together and it's some very
ordered arrangement but in fact all the
通往无限的方式，模式从不重复，它是有序的但不重复
way out to infinity the pattern never
repeats it's a ordered but non repeating
图案，有些具有这种特性的材料被称为
pattern and there are materials that
have this property that are known as
准晶体存在时间相当长，引起很大争议
quasi crystals it was very controversial
that they existed for quite some time it
实际上已经确定它们确实存在，并且获得了诺贝尔奖
has actually been determined that yes
indeed they do exist and the Nobel Prize
就在几年前被授予奖项的还有聚合物的想法
was awarded for it just a couple years
ago there's also the idea of a polymer
这是一维长而长的分子DNA，
which is sort of a one-dimensional long
very long molecule DNA is one that
您可能很熟悉，但是有很多聚合物，例如聚乙烯
you're probably familiar with but
there's many polymers like polyethylene
例如，聚合物具有许多其他特性
for example and polymers have a lot of
properties that are unlike other
我们可能会在一件事中熟悉的材料知道它们的流动性
materials that we might be familiar with
for one thing in you know their fluid
在那里，就像一碗意大利面，很多这样的串
phase there and sort of like a bowl of
spaghetti a lot of these strands sort of
全部混合在一起，就其而言，它们具有非常非牛顿的行为
all mixed in together and they have a
very non Newtonian behavior in terms of
他们的流体动力学，其粘度非常依赖于
their fluid dynamics that their
viscosity depends very strongly on the
您正在考虑的时间范围，因此如果您从未用过
timescales that you're considering so if
you've never done this experiment with
玉米淀粉和水，你可以混合一些玉米淀粉和水，
cornstarch and water you can sort of mix
up a goop of cornstarch and water that
会像液体一样倒，您可以像液体一样将手放在其中，但是如果您碰到
will pour like a fluid you can put your
hands in it like a fluid but if you hit
用锤子敲它会破裂，这真令人印象深刻，您知道问题是
it with a hammer it will crack it's
really impressive you know the issue is
那些长的绳子需要一些时间才能纠缠，所以如果您尝试
that that the the long strands they take
some time to unentangled so if you try
快速移动它们，他们会感觉很扎实，但是如果您给他们一些时间
to move them very quickly they'll feel
like a solid but if you give them time
放松一下，他们会彼此经过的，所以这只是一个
to relax they'll
past each other okay so that's just a
非常简短地浏览了凝聚态中的一些主题，我们可以
very brief tour through some of the
topics in condensed matter that we could
学习他们中的大多数，我们主要是不会学习的
study most of them we're not going to
study mainly we're gonna guess um ice is
冰是一种晶体，是真正的晶体，它是晶体的顺序。大多数形式的冰
ice is a crystal a genuine crystal it's
an order of crystal most forms of ice
大约有20种冰，其中大多数实际上是熟悉的
there's like 20 forms of ice most of
them are actually the ones were familiar
通常是结晶固体，它是有序的，但实际上
with is is generally a crystalline solid
it's all it's ordered but they actually
哦好吧，你的观点是，冰有点不同，因为
oh well okay there's you make a point
ice is a little bit different because
氢原子上的氢原子有一些重排
there's some slight rearrangement of the
of the oxygen hydrogen atoms on a
在微观层面上，它并非一直都是完美的周期性，而是
microscopic level it makes it not
perfectly periodic all the time but uh
但这主要是水晶，我们可以讨论一下微妙之处
but it's it's mainly a crystal we can we
can discuss the the the slight subtlety
与冰有关，使其略有不同是的，可以
associated with ice that makes it
slightly different yes okay
我们主要要研究的是晶体结构，结晶固体和
mainly what we're going to study is
crystal structure crystalline solids and
在我们出发之前，我先道歉一些，首先道歉的是
here before we get going I have a couple
of apologies the first apology is that
我将不得不使用很多PowerPoint幻灯片，而且我知道PowerPoint
I'm going to have to use a lot of
PowerPoint slides and I know PowerPoint
幻灯片很烦人，很难从PowerPoint幻灯片中学习，但是
slides are annoying it's difficult to
learn from PowerPoint slides but
不幸的是，我无法绘制出我要发布的所有幻灯片
unfortunately I can't draw this all the
slides that I post are going to be on
网页中的大多数以一种或另一种形式出现在书中
the web page most of them are in the
book in one one form or another
希望不是贝丝，而且讲座也将在网上进行
hopefully that wasn't Beth and the
lectures will be on online as well
希望这会给您足够的信息，以便能够学习
hopefully that will give you enough
information to be able to learn the
材料，这是第二个道歉
material
so that's the first apology the second
道歉在本讲课中尤其如此，我们将在下一讲中
apology is particularly in this lecture
and the next lecture we're going to have
遭受很多定义的困扰，这有点乏味，但是
to suffer through a lot of definitions
and that's a little bit tedious but
不幸的是，我们需要一种语言才能描述
unfortunately we need to have a language
in order to be able to describe the
我们正在谈论的事情，我们需要能够说出我们在这张照片中是什么
things we're talking about we need to be
able to say what is this picture we're
看原子坐在哪里，我们需要一些词汇来
looking at where are the atoms sitting
we need some sort of vocabulary in order
交流，所以我们将不得不忍受和遭受
to communicate so that's we're gonna
have to just bear with that and suffer
直到我们了解所有单词是什么，然后我们才能开始
until we until we understand what all
the words are and then we can start
再次向物理学进发第三道歉的第二个道理是
moving on with the physics again the
second of the third apology is that
不幸的是，并不是所有的书都对术语的正确定义达成一致
unfortunately not all books agree on
what the proper definitions of terms are
因此，您会发现有些书叫狗猫，有些书叫猫，
so you will find some books that call a
dog a cat and some that call it cat and
猴子，所以有点混乱我所用的术语是
a monkey so it's kind of a mess
the terms that I use are the ones that
是公认的牛津大学，它们实际上可能是最常用的
are generally accepted Oxford they're
actually probably the most commonly used
对于某些事物的术语，我将尝试指出存在某些情况的情况
terms for for certain things I will try
to point out cases where there is some
关于术语的含义或应使用的术语存在分歧，只是
disagreement as to what the terms mean
or what terms should be used but just be
警告您如果再看其他书，那么内部也有一些警告
warned if you look in other books then
and there's also caveats within within
我的教科书中有哪些术语存在争议，因此请注意
my textbook as so which terms are
controversial so just be warned of that
那是我们必须处理的问题之一，所以我们要
that that is one of the issues we have
to deal with okay so we're going to
从晶体的周期的第一个定义开始
start with the first definition of the
day a crystal crystal is a periodic
排列周期性排列通常是原子的含义，例如哎呀。
arrangement periodic arrangement usually
meaning of atoms so for example oops
这是一个水晶，所以这是左侧的一个简单水晶，然后您
that's a crystal so this is a simple
crystal over on the left and then you
右边有更复杂的晶体他们可以有很多不同的晶体
have more complicated crystals over on
the right they can have many different
原子的类型原子可以处于非常复杂的排列中，但只要
types of atoms the atoms can be in very
complicated Arrangements but as long as
它是周期性的，是晶体我实际上要去定义一个非常重要的定义
it's periodic is a crystal a very
important definition I'm actually going
给出这个词的几个定义，都等同于一个晶格
to give several definitions of this word
which are all equivalent a lattice so
定义a可能是最有用的，因为它是定义的一组点
definition a may be the most useful is
it's a set of points defined as defined
如
as
整数诗篇总和um这是另一个词原始格
integer Psalms sums um
here's another word primitive lattice
向量点阵向量好吧，现在这是一个案例，我将解释什么原始
vectors lattice vectors okay now here's
a case I'll explain what primitive
晶格向量在瞬间，但是在这种情况下，有一个词
lattice vectors are in a second but
here's a case where there's a word that
人们不同意原始语言，有时人们完全放弃这个词，他们
people disagree on primitive sometimes
people drop the word altogether and they
不要说有时候它的原理原理格子有时会被替换
don't say it sometimes it's principle
principle lattice is sometimes replaced
通过翻译，有时被单词基础代替
by translation and it's sometimes
replaced by the word basis that's a
特别不方便，因为我们完全使用词基这个词
particularly inconvenient because we use
the word basis for something completely
不同，使一个真正的混乱向量总是向量，另一个
different so that makes a real mess
vectors is always vector and the other
事实是，有些书会称其为brav而不是格子
thing is that some some books will call
lattice brav a lattice instead of
保留真正意义上的晶体的晶格，从而使晶格完整
lattice reserving lattice for really
meaning crystal so that makes a complete
一些人称其为晶格，而Bravo的晶格为晶格
mass some people call a crystal lattice
and the lattice of Bravo a lattice
请忽略那只是我的意思，这使所有事情都令人困惑
please ignore that that's just I mean it
makes everything incredibly confusing
无论如何，这是一套很好的定义，我们将在牛津考试中使用
anyway this is a good set of definitions
that we will use here at Oxford the exam
委员会同意这些定义，因此希望不会太过
committee agrees with these definitions
so hopefully it won't get too
复杂，我们只需要处理它，因为这就是世界的方式
complicated we just have to deal with it
because that's the way the world is
好吧，让我们让我实际定义这些晶体的例子
okay so let's let me actually define
give examples of what these crystals
这些晶格是什么，所以我们在一维中进行了此操作，您有一排点
what these lattices are so we did this
in 1d you have a bunch of points lined
在1d内它们之间的距离为a，这样我们就可以写出
up in 1d with a distance a between them
so then we can write the positions are
点阵中n的整数倍，aa是a，这里是
of the points in the lattice as n an
integer times a a is the a here is the
原始晶格因子prim lat BEC实际上我会经常称其为plv
primitive lattice factor prim lat BEC
actually I'll frequently call that plv
原始晶格向量，然后n是整数，所以这是我们
primitive lattice vector and then n is
an integer so this is something we've
在我们有整数倍原始格之前看到
seen before
we have integer times primitive lattice
因素给了我们点阵的点对不起，我在二维中赢了一点
factor it gives us the points in the
lattice sorry I won in 2d a little bit
比较复杂，所以晶格点最后的向量是整数
more complicated so the lattice points
the last vectors here are integer
基本格向量a 1加一个整数，2有时是另一个
a primitive lattice vector a 1 plus an
integer and 2 sometimes another
原始晶格矢量a 1 A是PL v的原始晶格矢量
primitive lattice vector a 1 the A's are
the primitive lattice vectors the PL v's
A应该是a应该是非共线的非共线的，所以我们有
the A's should be a should be non
collinear non collinear so that we have
真正是二维的，末端是整数，我们
something that's really two-dimensional
and the ends are integers and our
整数元素一些整数可以，所以让我们展示一个这样的例子
integers element some integers
okay so let's show an example of this so
这里我们有一个晶格，我们可以1和2是原始晶格
here we have a lattice and we can a 1
and a 2 are the primitive lattice
向量，如果我们认为中心点是每个点零
vectors if we think of this point in the
center as being the point zero every
该晶格中的点是一个整数，该整数是1加上一个的整数
point in this lattice is an integer
that's an integer times a 1 plus an
整数乘以2，例如，这里的点是1加1等于2，然后
integer times a 2 for example this point
here is to a 1 plus 1 a 2 okay and
通常，我们会在方括号中将R等于n 1逗号n 2表示为
frequently we will notate R equals n 1
comma n 2 in square brackets to indicate
n 1乘以1加n 2乘以2就像这里所示2逗号1到
n 1 times a 1 plus n 2 times a 2 like
it's indicated up here 2 comma 1 to
如果现在将此点视为原点，请指出这一点
indicate this point if this point here
is taken to be the origin now I should
还评论说这种符号经常被滥用，有时人们
also comment that this notation is
frequently abused that sometimes people
会说点1/2逗号0或类似的意思是一个点
will say the point 1/2 comma 0 or
something like that to mean a point
这不是晶格点晶格点之间的点
which is not a lattice point the point
which is in between lattice points so if
您想在此处指定此点，您会说走距离的一半
you want to specify this point here you
would say go a half the distance of the
原始晶格矢量a 1更重要的是它们是正方形
primitive lattice vector a 1 the more
important thing is that they're square
方括号表示空间中的一个点，如果此处为整数系数，则表示
brackets mean a point in space and if
integers coefficients here then you mean
一个晶格点，如果它不是整数系数，那么它不是晶格
a lattice point if it's not integer
coefficient then it's not a lattice
到目前为止，还可以，很好，很简单，我们可以做同样的事情
point okay so far so good all right so
far pretty easy we can do the same thing
在3d 3d中，我们将R等于N 1 a 1加n 2 a 2加n 3 a 3，而A等于
in 3d 3d we would write R equals N 1 a 1
plus n 2 a 2 plus n 3 a 3 and the A's
应该是非共面的
should be non coplanar
non
共面的，所以我们谈论的是三维的
coplanar so that we're talking about it
something that's three-dimensional and
我们可以将其记为R，因为R等于方括号，而一，二和三等于那个
we can notate it as R equals brackets
and one and two and three like that one
您应该知道的是原始晶格的选择
thing that you should be aware of is
that the choice of primitive lattice
POV的向量原始格向量不是唯一的，因此您可以选择
vectors of POVs primitive lattice
vectors is not unique so you can choose
不同的原始晶格矢量集，它们完全可以
different sets of primitive lattice
vectors and they're perfectly okay for
例如，您可以选择这两件事作为原始晶格矢量
example you could choose these two
things as primitive lattice vectors you
可以选择这两件事作为原始晶格矢量
could choose these two things as
primitive lattice vectors you could
选择这两件事作为原始晶格向量，重要的是
choose these two things as primitive
lattice vectors the important thing is
晶格上的任何点都应表示为整数
that any point on the lattice should be
expressible as an integer some of the
原始晶格向量还可以，到目前为止一切都很好，首先有机会获胜
primitive lattice vectors okay so far so
good all right first chance to win
神话般的奖赏是这些原始晶格矢量，好吧，谁是第一个
fabulous prizes are these primitive
lattice vectors okay who is the first
有人说我听说还可以，不，不，你不是别人吗？
one to say I heard it's okay no no you
weren't someone someone someone else
在这里，你还好，你们这样的骗子，好吧，所以我有些声音
over here it was you okay you guys such
liars so all right so I was some voice
在这里我听到了，但是我不知道是谁把它给你的
over here I heard it over here but I
don't know who gave it to you all right
再有一个机会好吧，是的，这些是原始晶格向量
one more chance okay yes these are
primitive lattice vectors it's its
晶格矢量，因为您可以通过某种方式到达晶格中的任何点
lattice vectors because you can get to
any point in the lattice by some sort of
整数一些原始晶格向量，好吧，这些
integer some of those primitive lattice
vectors okay how about these so these
原始晶格向量不，它们不是，所以不是，因为如果添加它们
primitive lattice vectors no they're not
so they're not because if you add them
以所有整数组合在一起，他们会错过所有其他晶格点
together in all integer combinations
they miss every other lattice point okay
如果我拿走了一半，它们将是这个晶格的原始晶格矢量。
they would be primitive lattice vectors
for this lattice if I took away half the
晶格点，那么你就拥有杰出的廖的向量，好吧，大家
lattice points then you have preeminence
Liao's vectors okay all right everyone
总是错过每年一个可以的状态，所以第二个定义晶格
always misses that one okay every year
okay so a second definition of a lattice
晶格的等价定义的晶格种类这是B是它是a
a lattice sort of equivalent definition
of a lattice this is B is that it is a
还可以
okay addition
哦，让我们看看，也许它会改变它是一组向量
oh let's see uh maybe change it it's a
set of vectors set of vectors such that
两个中的两个相加得到第三个
addition of two of two gives a third
好的，这实际上很容易看出，这等同于
okay and this actually it's pretty easy
to see that this is equivalent to the
如果您对两个都是整数的n1个逗号N有一个先前的定义，则为
prior definition if you have n1 comma N
to both of those being integers so it's
晶格的元素，然后将它们添加到n 3逗号n中
an element of the lattice and you add it
to n 3 comma n for both of those being
整数，所以它是ibadis的元素，得到n 5和6，然后是
integer so it's an element of ibadis you
get n 5 and 6 and those are then
那里的整数也代表晶格的元素以及第三个定义
integers also in there for an element of
the lattice as well a third definition
看到的是，从观看到观看，格子看起来都一样
see is that a lattice looks the same
looks the same from viewed from viewed
从任何晶格角度来看都可以，例如，如果我坐在这里
from any lattice point okay so for
example if I sit myself here so this
如果我坐在这里，然后观察环境，现在的事情就成了格子
thing is now is a lattice if I sit
myself here and I view the environment
我周围我说好吧，我左边有一个点，这个距离有一个
around me I say okay there's a there's a
point to my left this distance has a
指向右边的距离与指向上点的距离相同右上左下右下
point to the right the same distance as
a point up right up left down right down
左边，我可以测量距离，我可以测量角度，如果我坐下
the left and I can measure the distances
I can measure the angles and if I sit
这里的另一个晶格点具有完全相同的环境
here another lattice point over here it
has exactly the same environment to
指向右指向左指向右上右上左下右
point to the right to point to the left
point to the up right up left down right
左下完全相同的距离完全相同的晶格
down left exactly the same distance is
exactly the same lattice it's exactly
如果对于这些点中的每一个都是对的，则每个角度相同
the same angles if every if this is true
for every one of these points then what
你有一个格子好吧，例如，这个格子知道谁是谁
you have is a lattice okay so for
example is this a lattice know who's who
我听说那是谁在那边，但是那是你哦，好吧，好吧
that I heard that it's over here who is
it but it was a you oh okay all right
争取一切都好吧，所以我必须放弃其中一些，我已经像六个
fight for all right okay so um I have to
give up some of these I have like six
好的，这不是格子，
over here all right
so okay this is not a lattice and
有几种方法可以查看为什么它不是晶格，所以首先
there's several ways to see why it's not
a lattice so first of all from the first
定义是原始格向量，我们可以将它们加起来
definition are they're primitive lattice
vectors which we can add up in all
整数组合，它们将恰好给出这些点，并且仅给出这些点
integer combinations which would give
exactly these points and only these
指出当某些与整数系数在一起时不是，但是
points when some together with integer
coefficients well they're aren't but it
可能不太明显，以至于您可以尝试提出两个
may not be so obvious to see that that's
true that you can try coming up with two
您想要的原始晶格矢量，看看我们是否可以提出
primitive lattice vectors that you want
to may to and seeing if we can come up
这些点，只有这些点，你做不到，但是要容易得多
with these points and only these points
you can't do it but it's much easier to
使用其他一些这样的定义
use some of the other definitions like
this one
如果我们认为这里的这一点为零，我们应该有
we should have if we sort of think of
this point here as being zero then we
对它们求和时，在此晶格矢量中具有此晶格因子
have this lattice factor here in this
lattice vector here when you sum them
他们在一起应该给出第三个晶格向量，但是如果将这两个相加
together they should give a third
lattice vector but if you sum these two
在一起，您会在此六角形的中间得到一个点，但它不在那里
together you get a point in the middle
of this hexagon and it's not there
这不是我们集合中的要点之一，所以这不是晶格，因为您
that's not one of the points in our set
so this is not a lattice because you
不能将两件事加在一起，总是得到第三点，第三个定义是
can't sum two things together and always
get a third the third definition is that
如果我们所有的环境都应该是
the environment of our if the
environment of all points should be the
和我们的环境不一样，因为公关的环境
same and the environment of our is not
the same as the environment of P R has a
有一个指向南方的点，而P指向它的南方而不是它的南方
has another point to it South whereas P
has a point not to its South but to its
北，所以等价点P和Q中的P n R等价，所以即使在
North so P n R in equivalent points P
and Q are equivalent okay so even among
专业文学界人士将这个东西称为六角形
the professional literature people will
refer to this thing is the hexagonal
格子，这是错误的，它不是格子，您不应该将其称为
lattice and that's just wrong it's not a
lattice you shouldn't call it the
六角形的格子，尽管人们总是这样做，但我对此有所警惕
hexagonal lattice although people always
do so be warned about that I know this
令人震惊的是，您知道给人所有这些警告，而人们却说这些
is horrible to be you know giving you
all these caveats that people say these
事情总是出错，但是确实如此，所以让我们继续吧
things wrong all the time but it's just
true they do okay so let's go on fact
任何周期性结构都是
any periodic structure is a lattice of
重复的图案好吧，任何周期性的，这仅仅是事实，任何周期性的结构都是
repeating motifs okay any periodic this
is just a fact any periodic structure is
重复图案的格子，所以这是我在书中的同一幅画
a lattice of repeating motifs so here's
my business same picture in the book I
就像这些东西一样，它们就是犰狳，所以你有这个
just like these these things they're
armadillos I guess so this you have this
犰狳的周期性结构，实际上，如果在这里取一个格子
periodic structure of armadillos and in
fact if you take a lattice here the
试图由一堆三角形组成，这是一个
trying
made up of a bunch of triangles it's a
漂亮的格子，您用犰狳替换了所有这些点
nice lattice and you replaced each of
these points with an armadillo you get
整个周期结构，所以我将其绘制为晶格乘以重复
the whole periodic structure so I've
drawn it as lattice times the repeating
这是犰狳的结构，这当然是一个
structure which is the armadillo well
what about this this is certainly a
周期性结构，所以我们可以看到这东西实际上是
periodic structure so can we see how
this thing is actually a lattice of
重复图案，好吧，我声称这是一个三角形的格子
repeating motifs okay I claim that it's
a triangular lattice this triangular
带有蓝色圆点的晶格乘以这个重复的图案，而事实并非如此
lattice with blue dots times this
repeating motif and that might not be so
显而易见，但让我们看看是否可以使其变得明显，所以首先我要做什么
obvious to see but let's see if we can
make it obvious so first what I'm going
要做的是，我将在每个垂直边缘的中间放置一个大红点
to do is I'm going to put a big red dot
in the middle of each vertical edge okay
所以这是一个大红点这里是大红点，现在看起来有点
so here's a big red dot here are big red
dots and now it's looking a little bit
首先，这些大红色点很可能明显形成了
more likely that first of all these big
red dots are clearly forming a
像这个三角形格子一样，现在让我们
triangular lattice just like this
triangle lattice down here now let's
通过在其周围放置绿色菱形使其更明显
make it a little bit more obvious by
putting a green diamond around this
重复的主题，您可以看到，实际上，如果我将这些绿色堆叠在一起
repeating motif and you can see that in
fact if I stack together these green
钻石中的每一个都集中在这些大红色点上，它将重建
diamonds each one of them centered on
these big red dots it will reconstruct
整个蜂窝这个东西，人们称之为六角形格子，
the entire honeycombs this thing that
people call the hexagonal lattice that
不是格子，所以应该叫做蜂窝，我想是
isn't a lattice so it should be called
the honeycomb I guess all right is that
显然还可以，很好，到目前为止，很好，使我们进入了另一个非常有用的状态
that clear okay good good so far so good
so that brings us to another very useful
定义是单位晶胞单位晶胞等于它的空间区域
definition which is a unit cell unit
cell equals a region of space it
基本上，这是重复的图案，是空间与空间之间的区域
basically it's the repeating motif it's
the region of space from space which
当重复
when repeated
并堆叠在一起
and stacked and stacked together
有时我们使用平铺一词来表示重复，平铺是指重复，
sometimes we use the word tiled meaning
repeated tiled means repeated and
堆叠在一起重建了我们使用的这个完整的完整周期结构
stacked together reconstructs the full
full periodic structure we use this term
以前在一维的晶胞现在我们可以
unit cell
previously in one dimension now we can
只需在一般尺寸上使用它，这样绿色的钻石就会成为单位
just use it in general dimensions so
this green diamond would be the unit
这个重复结构的单元格好，让我们看看是否可以做另外一个
cell for this repeating structure okay
and let's see if we can do another one
这是我们的犰狳，所以我们有一个单元格，其中包含一个犰狳
here's our armadillos again so we have a
unit cell which contains one armadillo
我们可以将它们堆叠在一起对于晶胞重要的是
we can stack them together what's
important about unit cells is they have
没有空间堆叠在一起，它们应该像浴室瓷砖一样
to stack together with no space they
should be like bathroom tiles they
应该完全放在一起，彼此之间没有空格。
should fit together exactly with no
space between them another definition
这是一个有用的原始单元格
which is useful is a primitive unit cell
晶胞等于包含
unit cell equals a unit cell containing
正好一个晶格点正好一个晶格点
exactly one lattice point exactly one
lattice point so for example in this
图片，这将是一个基本单位晶胞，因为它包含一个大红点
picture this would be a primitive unit
cell because it contains one big red dot
那是晶格点，好吧，所以我们在这里看不到晶格点
and that's the lattice point and okay so
we can't see the lattice points in here
但是，如果您还记得它们的位置以及那些蓝色图片，
but if you remember where they were and
those those blue pictures the the
犰狳位于晶格点的顶部，因此每个晶胞都包含
armadillo is sitting on top of the
lattice point so each unit cell contains
我猜这恰好是一个晶格点这是另一种情况
exactly one lattice point I guess here's
here's another case here's a nice
晶格中有一个原始的晶胞，因为如果不能，我将全部
lattice there's a primitive unit cell
because it's if you can't I'll hole all
您将它们放在一起的所有空间都平铺在一起，每个单元格包含
space with it you put them together tile
all spaced and each unit cell contains
一个晶格点，但是如果原始晶胞会被警告
one lattice point however one should be
warned if the primitive unit cell
基本单位单元
primitive unit cell
单元格不是唯一的，您要使用的内容有不同的选择
cell is not unique you have different
choices as to what you want to use for
例如，您的原始晶胞是这样写的，您知道四个
your primitive unit cell for example
here's the lattice written you know four
不同的时间，您可以选择原始单位晶胞为任意形状
different times and you can choose
primitive unit cells to be any shape so
您可以选择他们，这个形状，这个形状，这个形状，只要
you can choose them this shape this
shape this shape this shape as long as
它们可以放在一起并平铺所有空间，您拥有一个非常漂亮的原始单位像元
they fit together and tile all of space
you have a very nice primitive unit cell
好吧，其中一些比其他更方便
okay some of them are more convenient
than others one should be warned that
像这样的东西也是一个很好的原始晶胞，这有点
something like this is also a good
primitive unit cell and that's a little
不太明显，它仅包含一个晶格点，但您必须考虑
less obvious that that contains exactly
one lattice point but you have to think
关于像这个家伙一样被部分封闭在单元格中的东西
about the the things that are partially
enclosed in the unit cell like this guy
因为仅计为整个圆的theta的theta，而这个计为
as only counting as theta of this the of
the full circle and this one counts as
整个圆的theta是pi减去的圆的theta是
theta of the full circle this one is pi
minus theta of the full circle this is
PI减去完整theta整个圆，如果您收集了所有这些
PI minus full theta the full circle and
if you collect all those pieces of the
将它们放在一起的晶格点，您将获得完整的两个pi，所以
the lattice point you put them together
you'll get the full two pi okay so it's
一个晶格点，但它分成四个部分，好吧，这是一个晶格
one lattice point but it's broken up
into four pieces okay it's one lattice
点分为四部分，也许这是一个很好的原始单元
point broken into four pieces maybe this
one this is also a good primitive unit
单元格，这是一个晶格点，更明显地分为两部分
cell this is a lattice point more
obviously broken into two pieces you
将它们组装在一起，您会得到一个晶格点，而这是一个
assemble them together you get the one
lattice point back and this one is a is
一个更简单的晶胞，可能更容易看到它包含
a simpler unit cell which is maybe
easier to see that that contains exactly
一个格子点另一个定义，我知道我们有很多
one one lattice point
another definition I know we have a lot
这些常规单位单元中的“我等于1”等于
of these conventional unit cell
I mean it's l equals conventional is
方便的单位晶格非原始单位晶格非原始单位晶格
convenient a unit cell a non primitive
unit cell non primitive unit cell that
很方便，通常意味着通常会遇到正交轴
is convenient which usually means
usually meeting orthogonal axes
正交正交轴就这么认为，例如，在这里，我们有一个
orthogonal orthogonal axes right think
so so for example here we have a
三角形晶格和具有正交轴的常规单位晶胞
triangular lattice and a conventional
unit cell here with orthogonal axes
而不是原始的晶胞，所以其中可以有多少个晶格点
rather than primitive unit cell so how
many lattice points are in that can
那里有人吗有人回来吗好吧，是的，我相信
someone up there who is it someone way
back there all right oh yeah I believe
你可以看起来诚实吗，是的，好的
you
could you look honest okay so yes okay
另一个另外一个定义啊，先生，这是葡萄酒商Seitz牢房里的大Nur Seitz
another another definition ah sir over
here a vintner Seitz cell big nur Seitz
如果您还没有碰到细胞大神经元，他就是一位非常重要的物理学家
cell big nur was a very important
physicist if you haven't run into his
塞兹（Seitz）的名字已经不那么重要了，但在该地区也很重要
name already Seitz was less important
but also important the region the region
围绕晶格点
around a lattice point
更接近那个格子点，然后再指向其他任何点，所以你就是你
closer to that lattice point that point
then to any other okay so you're you
有很多格子点，您想找到一个周围的原因
have a whole bunch of lattice points you
would like to find the reason around one
比任何其他晶格更靠近该晶格点的晶格点
lattice point that is closer to that
lattice point than to any other lattice
点，有一种方法可以做到这一点，那就是Vigna网站建设Vigenere
point and there's a way to do this which
is the Vigna sites construction Vigenere
网站，您如何找到该区域施工说明，我将
sites how you find that region
construction instruction which I will
解释这种结构，描述它比写出来要容易，但是
explain this construction it's easier to
describe it than to write it out but
我将使用垂直的垂直二等分线写下来，让我们看看
I'll write down use perpendicular
perpendicular bisectors so let's see how
我们这样做很好，所以这是格子，我标记了其中的点之一
we do this okay so here's the lattice
and I've labeled one of the points of
我们想找到那个格子的维格护士Seitz细胞
the lattice black we'd like to find the
Vig nurse Seitz cell of that lattice
换句话说，更接近黑色的空间区域是什么
point in other words what is the region
of space which is closer to that black
点阵比任何蓝色点阵都好，我们该怎么办
lattice point than is to any of the the
blue lattice points okay how do we do
好吧，你在这里选择一个相邻的点，然后把
that well you pick a neighboring point
like this one point up here and you put
沿垂直平分线向下，这条红线现在可以了
down a perpendicular bisector this red
line okay now everything on the lower
红线的一侧比蓝点更靠近黑点
side of that red line is closer to the
black point than it is to the blue point
标记了垂直等分线的一个正确定义现在让我们这样做
labeled one right definition of
perpendicular bisector now let's do that
在这一点上还有另一点，现在我们有了这个垂直
with another point over here this point
too and now we have this vertical
垂直等分线和的的左侧的所有内容
perpendicular bisector and everything on
the left hand side of the of the of the
垂直线比蓝点标签更靠近黑点
vertical line is closer to the black
point than it is to the blue point label
两个，而您对三个，四个，五个和六个以及所有
two and you do the same thing for three
and four and five and six and all the
进入您的墙的区域以及我在该区域中的所有内容
way around into you wall offer region
and everything in that region which I've
现在绿色比其他任何一个都更接近黑点
now colored green is closer to the black
point than it is to any of the other
蓝点好吧，那就是清楚它是如何工作的，好吧，那么你就有了
blue points okay is that clear how that
works okay good so then you have this
一个不错的区域，是一个维格纳·塞茨（Vigna Seitz）的牢房
nice region which is a Vigna Seitz cell
turns out that the big nurse sitesell is
首先，他的原始单位细胞框架甚至本身也很好
primitive his primitive unit cell frame
even itself well first of all it
显然只包含一个晶格点，因此非常适合平铺空间
obviously contains only one lattice
point so that's good at tiles space
因为您可以在空间的每个点周围放置一个大型的nur站点单元，
because you can put a big nur site cell
around every point in space and
显然，空间的每个点都是在vinner视觉单元中
obviously every point of space is the
bigness is in the vinner sight cell of
Vigna中的某个晶格点，无论最后一个点与您最接近
some lattice point whichever last points
is closest to you you're in that Vigna
视单元等等，在瓷砖空间，您可以关闭这一晶格点，
sight cell and so at tile space and you
can close this one lattice point and
这些中的每一个都具有相同的形状，所以它是一个很好的原始单元格
each one of these has the same shape so
it's a nice primitive unit cell okay
好，每个人到目前为止都开心，好吧，嗯，我要说的，我想这是
good everyone happy so far okay now um
I'm gonna this I think I think this is
不在课程提纲上，所以您真的不需要学习它，但是它很酷
not on the syllabus so you don't really
need to learn it but it's pretty cool
我卖的是borin吗？我可以正确地拼写胸罩吗？Noi Voronoi cell Voronoi
known as a borin do I sell to spell it
right bra Noi Voronoi cell Voronoi
Voronoi细胞是非晶格的大护士位点细胞
Voronoi cell which is a big nurse site
cell for a non lattice for a non lattice
点集的集合，因此，假设您在一个点中说了一堆点
collection of points points so imagine
you just have a bunch of points say in a
平面，并且您将区域隔离到比这些点更靠近点之一的区域
plane and you wall off the region which
is closer to one of the points than to
其他任何点Voronoi细胞的概念不仅在
any other other points this concept of a
Voronoi cell shows up not only in
物理在化学生物学中流行
physics it shows up in chemistry biology
epidemiology it shows up very heavily in
计算机图形显示在整个地方，包括比萨饼
computer graphics it shows up in just
all over the place including pizza
外送，所以我将向您解释为什么这对披萨外送很重要
delivery so I'm going to explain to you
why it's important for pizza delivery
您会发现为什么Voronoi单元是如此令人难以置信
and you will you'll realize why the
Voronoi cell is such an incredible thing
好吧，这就是这个程序，您可以单击它，知道它已链接到
so okay so this is this program you can
click you know it's linked to on my
网站，所以想象一下这张空白纸是牛津的地图，您一无所知
website so imagine this blank sheet here
is a map of Oxford you know nothing's
上面写着，您还拥有两家披萨店，其中一家在北部
written on it yet and you own two pizza
shops okay and one of them's in North
牛津，我们把它放在这里，其中一个在卡利外面，在这里，所以
Oxford we'll put it here and one of them
is out in Cali it's over here so that
蓝线是这两个之间的垂直等分线
blue line is the perpendicular bisector
between those two okay now if someone
打电话给你，说如果他们在这个地区附近，我要披萨
calls you up and says I want a pizza if
they're in this region they're closer to
这个红点，所以您在北牛津有个送货员，而如果
this red point so you have the guy in
North Oxford a deliverer whereas if it's
如果这个地区的情况很好
in if
it's down in this region well it's
接近这一点，所以您现在可以让那个家伙完成任务，
closer to this point so you have that
guy deliver now you're making a lot of
钱，所以您又买了几个披萨店，所以又放了几个
money so you buy a couple more pizza
shops so it's put in a couple more one
两个三个好吧，您有一堆披萨店，现在是Voronoi
two three okay you have a bunch of pizza
shops and now these are the Voronoi
每个红色点的单元格，所以这个区域在这里
cells of each of these red points so
this region here everything inside this
这里的区域最接近这个红色点，即它的Voronoi单元格，因此，如果有人
region here is closest to this red point
that's its Voronoi cell so if someone
呼叫此区域内最靠近他们的那个人为其服务，并且
calls within this region its serviced by
this this guy who's closest to them and
依此类推，依此类推，您可以继续进行下去，并添加点和
so forth and so on you can keep going on
and on and on and adding points and
这些单元格表明它的单元格始终围在
these cells indicate that it cells
always wall off the area which is
最接近那个红点，您可以猜测会有一个
closest to that red point and you can
kind of guess that there's going to be a
Voronoi细胞概念在数百万种不同的应用中有数百万个应用
millions of applications of the idea of
the Voronoi cell in lots of different
科学领域，包括披萨外送，这应该是一门科学
areas of science including pizza
delivery which should be a science by
现在好吧，这就是我们要说的关于Voronoi细胞的全部内容，所以接下来
now okay all right so that's all we have
to say about Voronoi cells so next the
词基，不应与我们在使用词基时混淆
word basis this should not be confused
with the word basis that we had when we
谈到原始格向量，有人称它们为原始
talked about primitive lattice vectors
and some people call them primitive
基向量不是这个，这就是为什么我们在我们不使用单词base的原因
basis vectors that's not this this is
why we do not use the word basis when we
谈论原始格向量，我们不称它们为原始基向量
talk about primitive lattice vectors we
don't call them primitive basis vectors
因为我们在此使用鸟形基准，对此混淆表示抱歉，所以基准是
because we use the bird basis here sorry
about that confusion okay so a basis is
相对于单元格中单元格中对象的描述
a description of objects in the unit
cell in unit cell with respect with
尊重RESP ECG尊重我们的参考晶格点
respect RESP ECG respect to our
reference lattice point
好吧，例如，哎呀，好吧，所以在这里我们有一个周期结构
okay so for example oops okay there so
here we have a periodic structure I've
将晶格作为参考晶格点，我在每个晶格中将其绘制为蓝色
put the lattice the reference lattice
point I've drawn it blue in each of
这些单元格，然后您必须描述单元中的所有内容
these unit cells and then you'd have to
describe everything that's in the unit
单元格指向那个晶格点，所以您会说有一个犰狳
cell reference to that one lattice point
so you would say there is an armadillo
坐在你的蓝点上面好吧，也许那不是那么有用，让我去做
sitting on top of your blue dot okay
maybe that's not so so useful let me do
一个更注重物理的晶体，所以这里是一个由两个晶体组成的晶体
a more more physics oriented one so
here's a crystal here made up of two
不同类型的原子，大的浅灰色原子和小的深灰色原子
different types of atoms the large light
gray atom and the small dark gray atom
好吧，参考点的黑点给了我
okay the black points of reference
points that give me the corners of the
单位单元，所以这里是单位单元，这里只是炸了一点，所以
unit cell so here's a unit cell and here
it's just been blown up a little bit so
您会看到更好的一点，所以在这里，我们在下一个单位单元中有一个单位单元，
you can see a little bit better so here
we have a unit cell next unit cell and
如果您将单位单元堆叠在一起，您将重建整个整体
if you stack the unit cells together you
would reconstruct the whole the whole
水晶现在的基础是我们应该列出该单元中的所有对象
crystal now a basis is that we should
list off all of the objects in the unit
参照参考晶格点的单元格，我们称其为零零
cell referenced to the reference lattice
point which we call coordinate zero zero
所以我们说，例如，在位置a上方有一个很大的浅灰色原子
so we would say for example there's a
large light gray atom at position a over
2a到这里关于这个点零零然后有小
2a over to here with respect to this
point zero zero then there are small
位置2的深灰色原子a over 4 over 4 3 over 4 over 4 3 3 over 4 3 over 4
dark gray atoms at position two a over 4
over 4 3 over 4 over 4 3 over 4 3 over 4
还有4分以上4分3分4分所以一旦我给你所有这些清单
and a over 4 over 4 so 3 over 4 so once
I've given you all of this list of where
所有对象都在单元格中什么是对象及其对象
all the objects are in the unit cell
what the objects are and what their
相对矢量相对于参考晶格点I然后给出
relative vector is with respect to the
reference lattice point I then giving
你的晶体基础很清楚，所以如果我告诉你晶格，我
you a basis for the crystal is that
clear so if I tell you the lattice and I
告诉你我告诉过你整个晶体的基础，所以这是我们使用的语言
tell you the basis I've told you the
whole crystal so this is the language we
现在需要描述整个晶体有时很有用，所以
need in order to describe the whole
crystal now sometimes it is useful ok so
在这里，使参考晶格与某些原子重合非常有用
here it's useful to take the reference
lattice to be coincident with some atoms
所以这是由红色和蓝色物体，红色和蓝色原子组成的晶体
so here's here's a crystal made up of
red and blue objects red and blue atoms
你知道你可以拿一个像这样的晶胞，它包含一个红色原子
you know you can take a unit cell that
looks like this it contains one red atom
在一个蓝色原子中，但是人们做得更多的是，他们将晶胞与
in one blue atom but what people do more
often is they put the unit cell with
红色原子的角，否则他们可能会选择蓝色，但在这种情况下，我们
corners on the red atom or they could
have chosen blue but in this case we're
要选择选择红色，然后我们会说我们的依据是红色原子在
gonna choose choose red then we would
say our basis is the red atom is at the
零晶胞的零位置，蓝色原子是
zero zero position
of the unit cell and the blue atom is a
与红色原子在a1方向上相距一半，因此它的位置为1/2
distance one-half in the a1 direction
from the red atom so it's a position 1/2
现在请注意逗号为零，请务必注意不要过度计数红色原子
comma zero now note it's really
important not to over count the red atom
所以你不要说零为零的红色原子，而1为另一个红色原子
so you don't say that there's a red atom
at zero zero and another red atom at 1
在1 1处将另一个红色原子清零在0 1处将要计数的另一个红色原子
zero another red atom at 1 1 another red
atom at at 0 1 that would be counting
四个红色原子，并且在该晶胞中只有一个红色原子被分割
four red atoms and there's only one red
atom in that unit cell it's divided up
分为四个部分，但是如果您只需要列出它一次为零零然后
into four pieces but if you only have to
list it once it's at zero zero and then
这意味着如果它为零零，那么所有其他部分也都是
it's implied that if it's at zero zero
it's also at all the other pieces it's
其他你知道它是四分之一的方式，如果它是它的一部分
other you know it's quarters the way
it's divided up if it's one piece of it
只是这里的其他部分会在那里，所以您不会超出列表
just here the other pieces of it are
going to be there so you don't over list
这是一个清晰的清单，它只是人们经常做出的事情
it is that clear list it just once it's
something people frequently make
好的错误，所以现在我们可以继续进行我们最终要建立的
mistakes on alright so now we can move
on to what we're finally building up to
3d晶格所以这是3d晶格最重要的说法
3d lattices 3d lattices so this is an
important statement may be the most
重要的声明，我将整天不让您知道
important statement I will make all day
you will not need to know to know by the
您无需了解3D网格中的考试委员会的法令
decrees of the exam committee you will
not need to know about lattices in 3d in
轴与轴不正交的3d原因何在？
3d where axes axes are not not
orthogonal why well because then you
明年没有什么要学习的，不，我的意思是，这只是
wouldn't have anything to learn next
year no I mean the reason is it's just
因为它在代数上变得更加复杂，而且这仅仅是
because it gets a lot algebraically more
complicated and it was sort of just
考试委员会同意，第三年我们可以使用所有3D晶格
agreed upon by the exam committee that
in third year we can all the 3d lattices
只是为了防止我们陷入各种代数的
just to prevent us from getting just
knee-deep in all sorts of algebra of
我们只需要在三个维度上保持正交轴的角度，
angles we're just going to stick with
orthogonal axes in three dimensions and
据我所知，该规则从未被打破，所以我
and I think that that rule has never
been broken as far as I know so I've
有人告诉我这是一条艰难而快速的规则，所以您可以坚持下去，我希望它能继续存在
been told this is a hard and fast rule
so you can stick with it I hope it stays
是的，所以3D立方晶格中最简单的晶格我们通俗地称为
true so the simplest lattice in 3d
cubic lattice we colloquially call it a
立方晶格，但它可能更恰当地称为简单立方简单
cubic lattice but it's probably more
properly called simple cubic simple
三次或原始三次或三次-P表示原始，您可能知道
cubic or primitive cubic or cubic - P
for primitive and you probably know what
这个单元格看起来像这个单元格
this looks like it looks kind of like
this this unit cell for this unit cell
等于一个立方体单位晶胞等于一个立方体，看起来像这样有多少原子
equals a cube unit cell equals a cube
and it looks like this how many atoms
在那个单元格中有多少个最后点1好的，我想每个人都
are in that how many last points are in
that unit cell 1 ok I'd everyone's
大喊大叫，所以我不知道如何让这种巧克力让我自己开心
yelling out so I don't know how to give
this chocolate all happy to myself all
对，是的，这是一个一格点
right
so yes it's one one lattice point in
在那个晶胞中，这是一个原始晶胞，是它的1/8倍
that in that unit cell so that's a
primitive unit cell and it's 1/8 times
所有八个角中的每个角在单位单元格内可写为1/8
all of the eight corners each corner is
1/8 inside the unit cell we can write
以更合适的方式降低晶格点，使我们等于UV W乘以
down the lattice points in more proper
way that our equals UV W times the
网格边缘长度ay，其中UV和w UV W都是整数，现在我们可以
lattice the edge length ay where UV and
w UV W are all integers okay now we were
在一开始就告诉我们应该能够将晶格点写为
told at the beginning that we should be
able to write the lattice points as
基本晶格矢量的整数和，因此我们可以选择一个等于a
integer sums of primitive lattice
vectors so we can choose a one equals a
1 0 0 a 2等于0 1 0和a 3等于1 0 0 1
times 1 0 0 a 2 equals a 0 1 0 and a 3
equals a 1 0 0 1 and these are the
原始晶格向量P LVS好的
primitive lattice vectors P LVS okay
good
还有一个词很有用，那就是协调的想法
there is yet another word it's useful to
know is the idea of a coordination
数字通常称为Z的数字，它是最接近的数字
number number number which is usually
called Z which is the number of nearest
邻居
neighbors
那么这个立方晶格的协调数是多少？有人说六个
so what's the coordination number of
this cubic lattice someone said six who
是第一个说六个在这里的人哦，好吧，我相信你，我相信你
is the first person to say six it's over
here oh okay I trust you I believe you
是这四种啤酒中的一种，它仍然味道很好，是很好的巧克力，所以
one of these four beers yeah it still
tastes good it's good chocolate so
其实你知道那个活着最古老的人类寿命基因的女人
actually you know the woman who lived
the oldest recorded human lifespan gene
盾牌同志一百二十四岁半她吃了一公斤
comrade shield one hundred twenty four
and a half years old she ate a kilogram
一周有两杯巧克力，维基百科上有两杯，所以好吧，实际上
of chocolate a week it's two it's on
Wikipedia so all right so actually the
简单立方简单立方晶格虽然它是
simple cubic simple cubic lattice
although it's um this is what it would
如果您将原子放在每个晶格点的位置上，
look like if you put atoms on the
position of each of the lattice points
虽然这是一个非常简单的格子来描述它，但它显然是一个立方体
it's a a cube obviously although this is
a very simple lattice to describe it's
实际上所有材料上所有原子的性质都极为不同寻常
actually extremely unusual in nature of
all the materials all the atoms on the
元素周期表只有一个元素实际上需要一个简单的三次方
periodic table only one only one element
actually takes a simple cubic
元素是po，还有一个发现discovered的人
arrangement the element is polonium and
for one more who discovered polonium
有人相信这是你的好，那是他的，是玛丽居里
some one over here was believed you okay
it was his it was Mary Curie and
lon以她的祖国波兰而得名
polonium was named after her home
country of Poland have to mention that
因为居里夫人是我的英雄之一，所以原因之所以
because Mary Curie is one of my heroes
all right so the reason the reason why
这是如此不寻常，您必须考虑一下堆叠到第二秒
this is so unusual you have to sort of
think about stacking to that second
球，如果您尝试将网球像放在盒子一样的东西中
spheres if you ever try to put like
tennis balls in a box or something
您会意识到他们真的不喜欢保持他们真正想要的位置
you'll realize they really don't like to
stay in this position they really want
填补中间的那个洞，在那个洞里有很多额外的空间
to fill that hole in the middle there's
a lot of extra space in that hole in the
中间的人会掉进那个额外的洞，另一种思考的方式是
middle and someone will fall into that
extra hole another way to think about is
是你知道有一种结合力想要真正获得这些原子
is that you know there's a bonding force
that wants to get these atoms really
彼此接近或相当接近，您认为很难
close to each other or fairly close to
each other you sort of think of as hard
试图吸引彼此的球，这不是真的想要
spheres that are trying to attract each
other that it's not really gonna like to
在中间留下一个很大的大洞，这是要填补的东西
leave that great big hole in the middle
something's going to want to fill that
孔，这就是为什么简单的立方晶格在纯净中非常不寻常的原因
hole so that's why the simple cubic
lattice is is very unusual among pure
元素，因此我们需要在简单立方晶格上存在一些差异
elements so there's some variance on the
simple cubic lattice that we need to
知道四方格子
know tetragonal lattice
这意味着垂直于边缘的垂直轴的轴相等，因此
which means axes perpendicular axes
perpendicular to edges equal equal so
画一幅画，所以这是简单的立方，在边缘处是四阶
draw a picture of that so here's simple
cubic here's tetr-a g''l to the edges
相等，一条边是不同的，另一条我们需要知道的是正交的
are equal one edge is different and the
other we need to know is orthorhombic
这是垂直于轴线的轴，没有边是相等的，所以我们走了
which is axis perpendicular no edge is
equal okay so there we go
简单正交的所有边长不同，但至少全部正交
simple orthorhombic all edge lengths
different but at least all orthogonal
现在，尽管简单三次在本质上是非常不寻常的，但有些事情
now although simple cubic is a very
unusual in nature there are things that
基于非常普遍的简单三次方，因此您需要了解
are based on simple cubic that are quite
common so you do need to know about the
简单的立方晶格，让我们回到这张图片，这里要记住这一点
simple cubic lattice so let's go back to
this picture here remember this very
如果您要引用多个原子类型，则非常方便
convenient if you have more than one
type of an atom to put the reference
晶格作为晶格点上的参考原子，然后是另一个原子
lattice as the reference atom at the
lattice point and then another atom you
可以引用它，但是您可以通过给出其位置来提供依据
can reference its but you can give a
basis by giving its position with
相对于参考点，参考点格非常重要
respect to the reference the reference
lattice point so a very important
结构就是所谓的氯化铯结构
structure is the so-called caesium
chloride structure named that way
因为氯化铯的材料明显具有这种结构
because the material cesium chloride
takes that structure obviously cesium
氯化物是一种非常离子化的物质铯放弃了它的电子
chloride it's extremely ionic material
cesium gives up it's an electron very
很好，而且氯极具负电性，所以它想
nicely and and chlorine is extremely
electronegative so it wants to take that
电子，所以你得到了很好的离子键，所以铯的定义
electron and so you get a nice ionic
bonding so the definition of cesium
氯化物结构是具有基本立方晶格或豌豆的立方晶格
chloride structure is cubic lattice with
the basis simple cubic lattice or a pea
具有基础的立方原始立方晶格，我们将铯放在
cubic primitive cubic lattice with basis
basis where we put the cesium at
晶格点的位置0 0 0和氯的位置1/2 1/2 1/2
position 0 0 0 on the lattice point and
the chlorine at position 1/2 1/2 1/2
那是我们在这张照片上的洞的中间，所以这
that's in the middle of the hole
that we had in this picture here so this
氯会填满那个孔，所以我们得到的看起来像
the chlorine is gonna fill that hole so
what we get is something that looks like
这是铯在晶胞和氯的角上
this we get the cesium's on the corner
of the unit cell and the chlorine
坐在晶胞的中央好
sitting in the center of the unit cell
okay
现在您可能会这样认为，铯的角上有铯
now you might think of it this way as
having cesium's on the corners of the
晶胞和在晶胞中心的氯，但这是
unit cell and the chlorine in the center
of unit cell but that's kind of
我们以这种方式选择它是任意的，因为如果您愿意，这是另一张图片
arbitrary that we chose it that way
because if you so here's another picture
具有相同结构的铯为白色，氯和氯为
of the same structure the cesium's are
white and the and the chlorines are
这里是绿色，这是我们刚刚在讨论铯的晶胞
green here so here's the unit cell we
were just discussing the cesium's on the
角落处有clora，中间有氯，但也有可能
clora on the corners and chlorine in the
center but one could just as well have
选择它作为角上有氯和铯的晶胞
chosen this as the unit cell with the
chlorines on the corner and the cesium
在中心，所以我们真正拥有的是两个互锁的简单立方晶格
in the center so what we really have is
two interlocking simple cubic lattices
其中之一是由铯组成的其中之一是由氯组成的
one of them is made up of the cesium's
one of them is made up of the chlorines
好的，这是一个动画，应该显示出来，所以
okay and here's a here's an animation
that's supposed to show that so that's
氯化铯这里是铯，这里又是氯化铯，还有
cesium chloride there's the cesium's
here's cesium chloride again and there's
那里的氯每个都是一个简单的立方晶格，它们有点像
there's the chlorines each of them is a
simple cubic lattice and they're sort of
粘在一起，所以这种结构的铯
stuck together
so this type of structure the cesium
氯化物结构实际上是自然界中很常见的结构
chloride structure is actually quite a
common structure in nature now we can do
还有一些事情要考虑纯铯纯铯
something else which is to consider pure
caesium pure cesium which is a very
相似的结构纯铯结构，所以我们有立方p晶格p
similar structure pure cesium structure
so we have so it's a cubic p lattice p
格，但我们可能要把它放在括号中，因为我们要
lattice but we may be may I'm gonna put
this in parenthesis because we're gonna
说这是铯的隐居时刻，我们将铯置于零零
say that's a lie-in moment cesium we're
going to put the cesium at zero zero
零，然后再以一半1/2 1/2的另一个铯，那么我们要做的就是
zero and then another cesium at one half
1/2 1/2 okay so all we're going to do is
我们将服用氯化铯，并摆脱
we're going to take that cesium chloride
and we're going to get rid of the
中间的氯，再用另一种铯代替，所以我们可以考虑
chlorine in the middle and replace it
with another cesium okay so we can think
它是简单的三次方，其基础是铯为零零
of it as simple cubic with the basis
where the basis is a cesium at zero zero
零和铯的一半1/2 1/2现在这实际上本身就是一个不同
zero and a cesium at one half 1/2 1/2
now this is actually itself a different
晶格的类型这是我们重要的晶格类型
type of lattice this is
important type of lattice that we're
将要研究的那个叫做体心立方晶格
going to be studying which well it's
known as the body centered cubic lattice
确保我不会错过任何以身体为中心的立方晶格
make sure I don't miss anything body
centered cubic lattice lattice also
被称为立方-我所以这个词居中居然不是听起来像
known as cubic - I so the word body
centered it's not it sounds like
瑜伽之类的东西，但是实际上你知道这个主意是
something out of yoga or something but
it's it's actually you know the idea is
那就是你在那个立方体的中心放了另一个点
that is that you've put a another point
in the center of the body of that cube I
来自德国内心的进入，这一定意味着任何德国学者
is from German inner is entry which must
mean something any German scholar it's
诸如此类的意思是在身体中心或某种形式
something like it means in the center of
the body or something kind of it anyway
所以我要声明所有这些点的所有环境都是
so I'm going to claim that all the
environment of all of these points is
完全一样，所以实际上它本身就是一个格子，让我们看看
exactly the same so this is actually
itself a lattice so let's see how this
这是如何工作的，这是体心立方晶格的晶胞
how this works this is the unit cell of
the body centered cubic lattice
在以人体为中心的立方晶格中有多少个晶格点-是的
how many lattice points are in the body
centered cubic lattice okay it's - this
是体心立方晶格的常规单位晶胞
is a conventional unit cell of the body
centered cubic lattice we take the
常规单位电池再次成为立方体，只是因为它更方便
conventional unit cell to be the cube
again just because it's more convenient
为此，显然在中心有一个，然后我们有一个
to do so there's one in the center
obviously and then we have the one which
在角落里分为八个部分，有一个方便的地方
is divided into eight pieces in the
corners now there's there's a convenient
描述这些三维结构的方法是使用已知的
way to describe these three-dimensional
structures which is to use what's known
作为平面图，平面图是来自某种建筑术语，其中
as a plan view a plan view is it comes
from a sort of architectural term where
您从顶部往下看，然后画出所指示的高度
you look down on the thing from the top
and you draw the heights you indicate
您所看到的所有事物的高度，因此，如果您身处其中，就知道
the heights of all the things that you
see so if you're up in a you know a
直升机，而您正在看不起这个常规的单元格
helicopter and you're looking down on
this conventional unit cell you would
在角落看到四件事，然后在中心看到一件事，然后
see four things in the corners and you
would see one in the center and then you
标记高度，因此将这一高度标记为a超过2，然后降低
label the heights so this one is labeled
with height a over two and then down
在这里它说未标记的点的高度为零，所以这个为零
here it says unlabeled points are at
height zero and a so this one's at zero
一个这个为零，这个一个为零，一个这个坐在这里
and a this one's at zero and a this
one's at zero and a this one sits here
在一个上，这个在一个高处--好的
on a and this one here is at height a /
- okay
如果将原子放到这个以身体为中心的立方结构中，它们将
if you put put atoms together in this
body centered cubic structure they would
看起来更像这样，实际上是
look more like this and and it's
actually it's
显然，它以这种方式填充了更多的晶格孔
it's clearly it's filling up much more
of the holes of the lattice this way
这是更有效的球体填充，并且有很多材料
it's much more efficient sphere packing
and there's quite a few materials that
实际上以这种以人体为中心的形式钠锂铁钾
actually take this body-centered form
sodium lithium iron potassium is many
还有很多，那么协调八号结束了
many many more so what is the
coordination number eight who's over
好的，好的，八点八点，所以如果你想到的话
there okay yeah okay eight it's eight so
if you think of it if you think it
假装你是中间的那个家伙，那么每个人都有八个邻居
pretend you're the guy in the middle
here then you have eight neighbors each
这八个邻居之一是不太明显的是，如果你碰巧是其中之一
one of those eight neighbors what's less
obvious is if you happen to be one of
这些在角落的家伙，你也有八个邻居，好吧，这里的每一点都是
these guys in the corners you also have
eight neighbors okay every point here is
完全相同，也许我会在这里展示，所以这是常规的单元格
identical maybe I'll show it here so
here's the conventional unit cell like
这就是中心点，现在您也可以选择
this and here's the point in the center
now you could just as well have chosen
这个点是一个立方体的中心，然后我们将这个立方体与
this point to be the center of a cube
and then we would have this cube with
这一点在中心还可以，所以请再次记住，这实际上是两个
this point in the center okay so again
remember that this is really two
当我们考虑它时，将简单的立方晶格互锁
interlocking simple cubic lattices when
we were thinking about it is being
氯化铯有两个互锁的简单立方晶格，所以如果
cesium chloride there were two
interlocking simple cubic lattices so if
我们选择该点作为中心，然后黄色的点围绕它
we choose this point as the center then
the yellow ones make the cube around it
如果我们选择一个作为中心，那么红色将围绕它
if we choose this one as a center then
the red ones make the cube around it
无论哪种方式，它总是有八个最近的邻居，好吧，我想的最后一件事
either way it always has eight nearest
neighbors okay the last thing I think
我们有时间我们下次再接，我们将证明这件事是
we're have time we'll pick up next time
and we'll prove that this thing is
实际上是根据我们在开始时给出的晶格定义得出的晶格
actually a lattice by the definitions of
lattice that we gave at the beginning of
好的一天，明天我再见[鼓掌]
the day all right I'll see you tomorrow
[Applause]